<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A protestation of the Kings supremacie Made in the name of the afflicted ministers, and opposed to the shamefull calumniations of the prelates.</title>
            <author>Bradshaw, William, 1571-1618.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16618</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3525</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120445</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855642</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855642</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21143</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16618)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21143)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 702:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A protestation of the Kings supremacie Made in the name of the afflicted ministers, and opposed to the shamefull calumniations of the prelates.</title>
                  <author>Bradshaw, William, 1571-1618.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[W. Jones's secret press]],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[England :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed 1605.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By William Bradshaw.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Puritans --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21143:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21143:1"/>
            <p>A PROTESTA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION OF THE KINGS SV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie.</p>
            <p>MADE IN THE NAME OF the afflicted Miniſters, and oppoſed to the ſhamefull Calumniations of the Prelates.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſa. 7.3.5.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Lord my God if I haue done this thing, if there be any wickednes in my hands, Then let the Enimie perſecute my Soule, and take it, let him tread my life downe vpon the earth, and lay mine honour in the Duſt. Selah.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Ioh. 18.23.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>If I haue spoken Evill: beare witnes of the Evill, But if I haue spoken well why ſmiteſt thou mee.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed <hi>1605</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21143:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE CIVILL STATES</hi> of this Kingdome.</head>
            <p>WE beſeech your <hi>H.</hi> and <hi>W.</hi> that you would by this true light that wee ſhall giue vnto you, looke into our innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. His Excelent Maieſtie, your ſelues, and your Sacreed Thrones are exceedingly abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, with Foggs and Miſts, which (breathed out of the mouthes of the Prelates) are caſt between your eyes, and the Integritie of our cauſe: through the darknes whereof you are led to giue many heavie Sentaunces a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the moſt harmles Subiectes in the Kingdome, as Enimies to the Supremacie and State. Whereas it ſhall appeare that no Chriſtians in the world giue more vnto the ſame then wee and that in very truth, the cauſe that we maintaine is for the King and Ciuill State, againſt an Eccleſiaſticall State, that ſecretly, and in a Myſtery (as we may hereafter haue occaſion to proue) oppoſeth it ſelfe againſt the ſame. If this proteſtation ſhall in any meaſure ſatisfie you. Then we deſire your Honorable Mediations for vs to the Higheſt. If not. That then we may know wherein it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiue and we ſhalbe found ready to giue all Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21143:2"/>
            <head>A PROTESTATION OF <hi>the</hi> Kings <hi>Supremacie.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVE <hi>hould and maintaine,</hi> the ſame Authoritie &amp; Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in all cauſes and over all perſons Ciuill and Eccleſiaſticall, graunted by Statute to Queene Elizabeth, and expreſſed and declared in the book of Aduertiſements &amp; Iniunctions, and in M. Bilſon againſt the Ieſuits, to bee due in full and ample man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner (without any limitation or qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) to the King and his Heires and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors for euer. Neither is their (to our knowledge) any one of vs, but is and euer hath been moſt willinge to <hi>ſubſcrib</hi> and <hi>ſweare</hi> vnto the ſame, accordinge to form of ſtatute, And we deſire that thoſe that ſhall refuſe the ſame may beare their owne iniqutie.</p>
            <p n="2">2 We are ſo far from Iudgeing the ſaide Supremacie to be vnlawfull: that we are perſwaded that the Kinge ſhould ſinne highly againſt God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ hee ſhould not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21143:3"/>the ſame vnto himſelf, &amp; that the Churches within his Dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſhold ſine da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nablie, yf they ſhould deny to yeald the ſame vnto him. yea though the ſtatuts of the kingdome ſhould deny it vnto him.</p>
            <p n="3">3 wee hould it plaine Antichriſtianiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me for any Churche or Church officers whatſoeuer, either to arrogate or aſſume vnto themſelues any part or parcel therof, and vtterly vnlawful for the king to giue away or alienate the ſame from his owne Crowne and dignitie to any ſpirituall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates or rulers whatſoeuer within or without his dominions.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Wee hould that though the Kings of this Realme weare noe members of the Church but very Infidels, ye and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the truth, that yet thoſe Churches that ſhalbe gathered together within thes dominions ought to acknowledge &amp; yeald the ſaid ſupremacie vnto them And that the ſame is not tied to their faith and Chriſtianitie but to their very Crowne from which noe ſubiect or ſubiects haue
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21143:3"/>power to ſeperate or diſioyne it.</p>
            <p n="5">5 We hould that nether King nor Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill ſtate are bound in matter of Religion to bee ſubiect and obedient to any Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall Perſon or Perſons whatſoeuer no further then they ſhalbe able to Conuince their conſciences of the truth thereof out of the word of God. Yea wee thinke they ſhould ſinne againſt God, yf they ſhould ground their Religion, or any part or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell therof vpon the bare Teſtimonie or Iudgement of any man, or of all the men in the world.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Wee hould that noe Churches or Church officers haue power for any crime whatſoeuer to depriue the king of the leaſt of his Royall prerogatius whatſoeuer, muche leſſe to depriue him of his ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie wherin the height of his Royall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnitie Conſiſts.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Wee hould that in all things Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this life whatſoeuer, the Ciuill Iuriſdiction of Kings and Ciuill States excelleth &amp; ought to haue preheminence
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21143:4"/>ouer the Eccleſiaſticall, and that the Eccleſiaſticall nether hath nor ought to haue any power in the leaſt degree ouer the bodies, liues, goods, or libertie of any perſon whatſoeuer, much leſſe of the Kings and Rulers of the Earth.</p>
            <p n="8">8 Wee hould that Kings by virtue of their Supremacie haue power: yea alſo that they ſtand bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by the lawe of God to make Lawes Eccleſiaſticall ſuch as ſhall tend to the good ordering of the Churches in their Dominions, And that the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ought not to bee diſſobedient to any of their Lawes, ſo far as in obedience vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, they doe not that which is contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry to the word of God.</p>
            <p n="9">9 Wee hould that though the King ſhal Command any thing contrarie to the Word vnto the Churches, that yet they ought not to reſiſt him therein, but onely peaceablie to forbeare obedience, and ſue vnto him for grace and mercie, and wher that cannot be obtained, meekely to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelues to the puniſhment.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:21143:4"/>
            <p n="10">10 Wee hould that the King hath po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer by virtue of his Supremacie, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue out of the Churches, whatſoeuer he ſhall diſcerne to be practiſed therin, not a greable to the word of God. And if he ſhal ſee any defect either in the worſhip of God or in the Eccleſiaſticall Diſcipline, he ought by his royall authoritie &amp; power to procure and force the redreſſe therof, yea, though it be without the conſent and a gainſt the will of the Eccleſiaſticall Gouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners themſelues.</p>
            <p n="11">11 <hi>Wee hould</hi> that the King hath as much author itie over the bodie, goods, &amp; affaires, of Eccleſiaſtical perſons, as of any other of his Subiects whoſoeuer. And that by his authoritie, he may force them not onely to all ciuyll dueties belonging vnto them, but alſo vnto all Eccleſiaſticall: af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictyng as great puniſhment vpon them for the neglect thereof, as vpon any other of his Subiects.</p>
            <p n="12">12 <hi>Wee hould</hi> that he hath power, to remoue out of the Churches, all Scando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21143:5"/>Sciſmaticall &amp; Hereticall Teachers, and by all due ſeueritie of Lawes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe them.</p>
            <p n="13">13 Wee hould that all Eccleſiaſticall Lawes made by the King (not repugnant to the word of God) doe in ſome ſorte bind the conſciences of his ſubiects: and that no ſubiect ought to refuſe obedience to any ſuch law.</p>
            <p n="14">14 We hould that the King onely hath power within his Dominions, to Couvene Synods or generall Aſſemblies of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, And by his authoritie Royall, to ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſie and giue life and ſtrength, to their Canons and Conſlitutions, without whoſe ratification, no man can force any ſubiect to yeald any obedience vnto the ſame.</p>
            <p n="15">15 Wee hould that though the King may force the Churches to be ſubiect and obedient vnto him: and to be Members of the Commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that the Churches ſeuerally or ioyntly, haue no power to force him: or any ſubiect, againſt their will to any ſervice vnto them, or to any religious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> whatſoeuer. No, nor to be ſo much
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21143:5"/>as a member of any Church.</p>
            <p n="16">16 Wee hould that the King ought not to be ſubiect to the Eccleſiaſticall Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of any Churches, Church officers or Synods whatſoeuer, but onely to that Church and thoſe Officers of his owne Court and Houſhould, vnto whom (in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence of their Religion and of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Graces of God he ſees ſhinynge in them) he ſhall of his owne freewill, ſubiect and commit the Regiment of his ſoule, in whom their can be, no ſuſpition nor feare of any partialitie: or vniuſt or rigorous dealing againſt him.</p>
            <p n="17">17 Wee hould that if any Ecclſiaſticall Gouerners (call them by what name you will) ſhall abuſe their Eccleſiaſticall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie in the execution of their Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, vpon any man whoſoeuer. That the King and Ciuill States vnder him, haue power to puniſh them ſeuerely for it, much more if they ſhall abuſe it vpon the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Maieſtie himſelfe.</p>
            <p n="18">18 If the King ſubiecting himſelfe: to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21143:6"/>Spirituall Guides and Governers, ſhall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards refuſe to be guided and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by them accordinge to the word of God, and lyuinge in notorious ſinne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out repentannce ſhall wilfully contemne and diſpiſe all their holy &amp; religious Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thes Gouernors are to refuſe to adminiſter the <hi>holy things</hi> of God vn to him, and to leaue him to him ſelf and to the ſecreat Iudgment of God, and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to reſigne and giue ouer that ſpirituall charge &amp; tuition ouer him, which by cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from God and the King they did vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake. And more then this they may not doe. And after all this, Wee hould that he yet ſtill retaineth, and ought to retaine, in tierly &amp; ſolidly, all that aforeſaide ſuprea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e power and authoritie ouer the Churches of this Dominion in as ample a manner as if hee were the moſt Chriſtian prince in the world.</p>
            <p n="19">19 Wee acknowledge <hi>King Iames</hi> to be our onely lawfull Soueraigne and vnto him to be due all the aforeſaid <hi>Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:21143:6"/>&amp; wee renounce &amp; abiure allopinions doctrins practicies whatſoeuer repugnant or contrarie to the ſame, as Anabaptiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call &amp; Antichriſtian. And wiſh they may be ſeuerely puniſhed.</p>
            <p n="20">20 Wee never refuſed obedience to any Lawes or commaundements of the King: or State whatſoeuer, but onely to ſuch as we haue proued or are readie to proue, (if we might be heard with indifferencie) to be contrarie to the word of God. And we are readie to take our Solemne Oathes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Throne of Iuſtice, that the onely cauſe of our refuſall of Obedience to thoſe Canons of the Prelates for which we are in preſent ſo extreamly afflicted, is meere conſcience, and a feare to ſinne againſt God: And that if by due forme of reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng we may be conuinced in our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of the contrarie, we are as willinge as any Subiects in the Realme to Obey and Conforme.</p>
            <p n="21">21 Wee refuſe Obedience onely to ſuch Canons as require the performaunce of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21143:7"/>ſuch Acts, &amp; Rites of Religion, as are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected and abandoned of all other reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches, as Superſtitious diſorders, Such, as are ſpeciall myſteries of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Antichriſtian Idolatrie, Such as haue been controuerted in the Church e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſince the laſt breakynge forth of the light of the goſpell, out of the cloude of Popery in Luthers time. Such as all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant writers &amp; defendors of our Faith beyond the Seaes, and moſt of our owne Countrime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue either in generall or par ticular condemned as vaine, idle, and vn profitable, Such as all the faithfull, and painfull Paſtors of this Realme: and in a manner all States &amp; degrees of the ſame, woulde be content were remoued: and ſweept out of the Church, and for which few or none are zealous but the Prelates, and their adherents.</p>
            <p n="22">22 We deny no authoritie to the King, in matters Eccleſiaſticall, but onely that which Chriſt Ieſus the onely Head of the Church hath directly, and preciſly appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21143:7"/>vnto himſelfe, and hath denyed to communicate to any other creature or creatures in the world. For we hould, That Chriſt a lone is the Doctor of the Church in matters of Religion, and that the word of Chriſt which he hath given vnto his Church, is of abſolute parfection containyng in it all parts of the true reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, both for ſubſtance and ceremonie, &amp; a perfect direction in all Eccleſiaſticall matters whatſoeuer. Vnto &amp; from which it is not lawefull for any Man or Angell, to add or detract.</p>
            <p n="23">23 We are ſo far from makyng claime of any ſupremacie vnto our ſelues (and thos eccliaſticall officers which we deſire) that we exclude from our ſelues &amp; them (as that of which we are vtterly vncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) all Princely &amp; Lordlie ſtate pomp &amp; power whatſoeuer, houlding it a ſinne for any whoſoeuer to excerciſe (no not by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from the magiſtrat) any authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ouer the bodie, Goods, liues, libertie of any man whoſoeuer for any crime or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21143:8"/>whatſoeuer. So that any one of the baſeſt and moſt inferior Ciuill officers in a Kingdome hath and ought to haue (in our iudgement) more authoritie and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ouer men then any or all the Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Officers in the ſame kingdom or in the whol world. Yea we hold that the hig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heſt Eccleſiaſticall Officer in the Church ought to be as ſubiect vnto the baſeſt Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill officers in the Kingdome, as the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Subiect in the Kingdome, And that they ought not by virtue of their office, to chalenge any freedome or immunity at all from any Ciuyll Subiection whatſoeuer, belonging to any common Subiect,.</p>
            <p n="24">24 Wee conſine and bound all Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall power within the limitts onely of one particular Congregation, houldinge that the greateſt Eccleſiaſticall power: ought not to ſtrech beyond the ſame, And that it is an arrogating of Princly Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie, for any Eccleſiaſticall Perſon, or Perſons whoſoeuer, to take vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſdiction over many
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21143:8"/>Churches, much more over whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and Provinces of Chriſtians.</p>
            <p n="25">25 We <hi>hould</hi> it vtterly vnlawfull for any one Miniſter to take vpon himſelfe, or accept of a ſole Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſdiction over ſo much as one Congregation. And therfore we hould that ſome of the ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enteſt and moſt honeſt and godlie men in the Congregation, ought to be choſen by the Heades of Families, to be adioynded in Comisſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as Aſiſtants to the Miniſter, in the Spirituall Regiment of the ſoules of that Congregation, of which he is the Paſtor.</p>
            <p n="26">26 We <hi>hould</hi> that theſe Eccleſiaſticall Officers being ſo choſen by the Church or Congregation, are to exerciſe over the ſaid Congregation only a Spirituall Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction and power, conſiſtyng in a careful overſight of the outward behavior of the Members of their Church, That it be not ſcandalous, offenciue, and vnbeſeemynge Chriſtians. And if any Member ſhalbe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquent, they are brotherly to admoniſh
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21143:9"/>him, ſhewing him the nature of his crime by the word of God, And if after two or three admonitions, he ſheew no tokens of ſorrowe and penitencie, then are they to deny vnto him the pledges and ſeales of of the Church, to wit the Sacraments. If this cannot humble him but that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue obſtinate in that ſinne, then they are by the mouth of the Miniſter in Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation (the whole Church conſentinge freely therto) denounce him to be no Me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Kingdom of Heauen, and ſo forbeare to haue any further charge ouer him, vntill God ſhall worke the grace of Repentannce, in him? in this manner they are to proceed againſt all apparent and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident crimes only, as Murder Adultery Theft Blaſphemie, Ribaldery Lying, Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, Profanation of the Sabothes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Diuine Worſhip. Diſobedience to the Ciuil Magiſtrate &amp;c. Nether ought the Extreameſt of the Eccleſiaſticall Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures any whit hinder the courſe of iuſtice that the Ciuill Magiſtrate is to excerciſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21143:9"/>againſt the ſame crimes for if a Traytor himſelfe ſhould bee penitent, the churche ought to forgiue him and lovingly to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace him as a Sonne, but the Magiſtrate ought to execute him, If he ſhould be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate in that crime: As the Magiſtrate ought to cutt him off from the Ciuill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of men, ſo ought the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (of which he is a Member) cutt him of from all ſpirituall Communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with them. If any one of the Eccleſiaſticall Officers themſelues ſhall ſinne, he is as ſubiect to the Cenſures of the reſt as any other mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber of the congregation. If they ſhall all ſinne ſcandolouſly either in the execution of their Office, or in any other ordinarie manner: Then the Congregation that choſe them freely, hath as free power to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe them, and to place others in their roome. If the Congregation ſhall erre, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in chooſinge or depoſinge of her ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Officers, Then hath the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uill Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate alone power and authoritie to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them for their fault, to compell them
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21143:10"/>to make better choyſe, or to defend againſt them thoſe Officers that without iuſt cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes they ſhall depoſe or depriue.</p>
            <p n="27">27 <hi>Wee</hi> hould that thoſe Eccleſiaſticall Perſons that make claime to greater po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and authoritie then this, Eſpecially they that make claime <hi>Iure Divino</hi> of po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wer and Iuriſdiction to medle with other Churches then that one Congregation of which they are or ought to be Members. Doe vſurpe vpon the Supremacie of the Ciuill Magiſtrate, Who alone hath and ought to haue (as we hould and maine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine) a power over the ſeuerall Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations in his Dominions, And who alone ought by his authoritie not onely to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe common Lawes and Canons of Vni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>formitie and conſent, in Religion and worſhip of God vnto them all, But alſo to puniſh the offences of the ſeuerall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, that they ſhall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitt againſt the lawes of God, the policy of the Realme, And the Eccleſiaſticall Conſtitutions en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted by his authoritie.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:21143:10"/>
            <p n="28">28 Wee hould that the Kinge ought not to giue this authoritie away or to com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitt it to any Eccleſiaſticall Perſon or Perſons whatſoeuer, But ought himſelfe to be as it were, Archbiſhop and generall Overſeer of all the Churches within his Dominions, And ought to imploye vnder him, his Honorable Counſell, his Iudges, Leiftenaunts, Iuſtices, Cunſtables &amp; ſuch like to overſee the Churches, in the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall diuiſions of their ciuill Regiments, viſiting them and puniſhing by their ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill power whatſoeuer they ſhall ſee amiſſe in any of them: Eſpecially in the Rulers and Gouerners.</p>
            <p n="29">29 For as much as no people are more hated perſecuted and wronged of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked world then the true Churches of Chriſt, Wee hould that no people in the Earth ſtand in more neede of the ciuill magiſtrate, then they. And that it is the greateſt outward blesſing they can inioye in this life, to liue vnder the Protection of their Swords and Scepters, and the greateſt cauſe of mourning when the ſame
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21143:11"/>ſhalbe bent againſt them. And we hould thoſe churches to be no true churches of Ieſus Chriſt That livinge in any cuntry, ſhall refuſe Subiection to the ciuill Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents and Gouerners of the ſame, be they (in reſpect of Religion) never ſuch Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Infidells.</p>
            <p n="30">30 Wee hould it vtterly vnlawfull, For any chriſtian Churches whatſoeuer, by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny armed force or power, againſt the will of the ciuill magiſtracie and State vnder which they liue, To erect and ſett vpp in publique, the true worſhip and ſervice of God, Or to beate downe or Suppreſſe any ſuperſtition or Idolatrie that ſhalbe coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tenaunced and maintained by the ſame. Onely, Every man is to looke to himſelfe, that he communicate not with the Euills of the times, induringe what it ſhall pleaſe the State to inflict, and ſeekinge by all honeſt and peaceable meanes all refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of publicke abuſes, Onely at the hands of Ciuill publicke Perſons, And all practiſes contrarie to theſe, we condemne as Seditious and ſinfull.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:21143:11"/>
            <p n="31">31 All that we craue of his Maieſtie &amp; the State, is, that by his and their permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and vnder their protection, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, It may be lawefull for vs, To ſerue and worſhip God in all things accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding to his revealed will, and the manner of all other reformed Proteſtant Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, that haue made ſeperation from Rome, That we may not be forced againſt our conſciences to ſtaine and pollute the ſimple and ſynere worſhip of God preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in his word, with any humaine Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions and Rites whatſoeuer, but that in Divine worſhip we may be actors onely of thoſe things that may for matter or man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner either ingenerall or ſpeciall be conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded out of the word of God. Alſo to this end that it may be lawefall for vs to exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite vnto them and vnto their Cenſure a true and Syncere Confesſion of our faith, containyng the maine Grounds of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, vnto which all other doctrines are to be conſonant: as alſo a Forme of Divi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e worſhip and Eccleſiaſticall Gouerment, in like manner warranted by the word, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21143:12"/>to be obſerued of vs all vnder any Ciuill puniſhment that it ſhall pleaſe the ſaide Maieſtie, &amp; State to inflict, vnder whoſe authoritie alone, we deſire to exerciſe the ſame: and vnto whoſe puniſhment alone we deſire to be ſubiect if we ſhall offend againſt any of thoſe Lawes and Canons that themſelues ſhall approue in manner aforeſaide, And our deſire is, Not to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God in darke corners, but in ſuch publicke places and at ſuch convenient times as it ſhall pleaſe them to asſigne, to the intent, that they &amp; their officers may the better take notice of Our offences (if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch ſhalbe committed in our Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, and aſſemblies) that they may pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the ſame accordingly. And we deſire wee may be ſubiect to no other Spirituall Lords but vnto Chriſt, nor vnto any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Temporall Lords but vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, whom alone in this Earth we deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to makeour Iudges &amp; Supreame Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners &amp; Overſeers in all cauſes Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal whatſoeuer renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cyng as Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, all ſuch Eccleſiaſticall powers as arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21143:12"/>and aſſume vnto themſelues vnder any pretence of the Law of God or man, the ſaide power which we acknowledge to be due onely to the Ciuill Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p n="32">32 So long as it ſhall pleaſe the King and Ciuill State (though to the great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation of their owne authoritie as wee may haue occaſion hereafter to proue) to maintaine in this Kingdome, the State of the Hierachie or Prelacie: We can (in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to his Maieſtie and the State, and in deſire of peace) be content without envie to ſuffer them to inioye their State &amp; dig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nitie, &amp; to liue as brethren, amongſt thos miniſters that ſhall acknowledg ſpiritual homage vnto their ſpirituall Lordſhips, paying vnto them all temporall dueties, of Tenthes &amp; ſuch like: yea and ioyning with them in the ſervice and worship of God ſo far as we may doe it without our owne perticular co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municating with them in thoſe humaine Traditions and Rites, that in our conſciences we iudge to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull. Onely we craue in all duetifull manner that which the very Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21143:13"/>yeldeth vnto vs, that for as much as they are moſt malicious Enimies vnto vs and doe apparantly thirſt either after our blood, or the Shipwracke of our faith and conſciences, that they may not henceforth be our iudges in theſe cauſes, but that wee may both of vs ſtand as parties at the barre of the ciuill Magiſtrate to bee tried in thoſe differences that are betweene vs, and that when they ſhall publickly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligne or flander vs or our cauſe, it may be lauful for vs in a dutiful, ſober, peaceable &amp; modeſt manner without perſonall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche or diſgrace: in as publicke manner iuſtifie our ſelus, &amp; then inſteed of that ſillie mockſeruice to the King of wearing a linnen rag vpon our backs or making a Chriſtes Croſſ vpon a babies face wee ſhalbe readie to performe and yeald triple homage ſervice, &amp; tribute vnto him, &amp; ſhall think our liues &amp; all that we haue to vile to ſpend in the ſervice of him and the Ciuill ſtate vnder him.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21143:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
